covering the week's top tech dorks like
pokriva ovonedeljne vrhunske usluge poput
Linux bias artist Simon wacker noticed
Primijetio je Linux pristranski umjetnik Simon Wacker
something unusual at a made a
nešto neobično kod made a
demonstration in Berlin
demonstracija u Berlinu
Google Maps showed that there was a
Google Maps pokazao je da postoji
massive traffic jam even though there
masivan zastoj u prometu iako tamo
were zero cars on the road soon enough
ubrzo su bili nula automobila na putu
wicked realized that it was the mass of
zli su shvatili da je to masa
people or more specifically their
ljudi ili tačnije njihove
smartphones that had inadvertently
pametne telefone koji su imali nenamjerno
tricked Google into seeing gridlock on
prevario je Google da vidi zaključavanje mreže
an empty street and then he decided to
prazna ulica i onda je odlučio to
do it himself where Kurt says quote the
uradi to sam tamo gdje Kurt kaže da citira to
question was if it might be possible to
pitanje je da li je to moguće
generate something like this in a much
generirati ovako nešto u mnogočemu
simpler way I don't need the people I
jednostavniji način da mi ne trebaju ljudi
just need their smart phones end quote
samo im treba pametni telefon krajnji citat
so he borrowed phones from friends and
pa je kod prijatelja pozajmio telefone i
rental companies until he had acquired
iznajmljivanje kompanija dok nije stekao
99 devices which he piled into a little
99 uređaja koje je malo zakucao
red wagon the plan was simple over the
crveni vagon plan je bio jednostavan preko
course of a day a worker would walk up
tokom dana radnik bi šetao gore
and down a given Street mostly at random
i niz određenu ulicu uglavnom nasumično
towing his smart phone packed wagon
vuče svoj pametni telefon spakovan karavan
behind him the effect wasn't
iza njega efekt nije bio
instantaneous it took Google Maps about
trenutačno je trebalo za Google Maps
an hour to catch up but eventually
sat vremena da se nadoknadi, ali na kraju
inevitably wiper had said that his wagon
brisač je neminovno rekao da mu je vagon
would create a huge long red line in the
stvorio bi veliku dugu crvenu liniju u polju
app indicating that a traffic had slowed
aplikacija koja ukazuje da se promet usporio
to a crawl even though there wasn't too
puzati iako nije bilo previše
any traffic at all he had effectively
svaki efektivni promet uopšte
tricked the system into thinking a
prevario sistem na razmišljanje a
series of large buses was crawling back
niz velikih autobusa puzao je nazad
and forth Google said in a statement
i dalje, rekao je Google u izjavi
quote traffic data in Google Maps is
navesti podatke o prometu na Google kartama je
refreshed continuously at thanks to
osvježava se neprestano zahvaljujući
information from a variety of sources
informacije iz raznih izvora
including aggregated and anonymized the
uključujući objedinjene i anonimne
data from people who have location
podaci o ljudima koji imaju lokaciju
services turned on and contributions
usluge uključene i doprinosi
from the Google Maps community end quote
iz završnog citata zajednice Google Maps
they note that while it had figured out
napominju da je, iako je to skužila
how to distinguish between cars and
kako razlikovati automobile od i
motorcycles it does not yet have any way
motociklima ona još uvijek nema načina
to filter for a wecord setup wecord says
za filtriranje za postavljanje diska, kaže Wecord
quote what I'm really interested in
citirajte šta me zaista zanima
generally is the connection between
općenito je veza između
technology and society and the impact of
tehnologije i društva i uticaja
technology how it shapes us end quote
tehnologija kako nam oblikuje krajnji citat
the hack is getting attention not only
na hack se privlači pažnja ne samo
because it's fun but also serves as a
jer je zabavna, ali služi i kao a
necessary reminder that the systems
potreban podsjetnik da su sistemi
people take for granted involve inputs
ljudi uzimaju zdravo za gotovo uključuju inpute
and outputs and that they themselves are
i rezultati i da su oni sami
sometimes both
ponekad i jedno i drugo
it shows how simple it is to be it's how
pokazuje kako je jednostavno biti to kako je to
simple it is to fool a product in which
jednostavno je zavaravati proizvod u kome
people place a tremendous amount of
ljudi stavljaju ogromnu količinu
trust how this interesting there's a lot
vjerujte kako ovo zanimljivo ima puno
of fun but I love how the artist has
zabave, ali volim kako umjetnik ima
found the spin to say hey maybe we're
našao sam spin kako bi rekao da smo možda
trusting the technology a little too
verujući malo i tehnologiji
much that out so much so that anyone
toliko toga da bilo ko
looking at their app or using their GPS
gledajući njihovu aplikaciju ili upotrebljavajući njihov GPS
that's powered by Google services yes is
koje pokreću Google usluge da
avoiding those areas based on his little
izbjegavajući ta područja na temelju njegovih maloga
experiment right so when when I had
eksperimentirajte tačno pa kad sam imao
first heard this story I thought to
prvo sam čuo ovu priču na koju sam pomislio
myself okay so four people are in a car
sam dobro, pa su četvero ljudi u autu
like if you're carpooling and you're
kao da putujete automobilom i jeste
stuck in a slow section of the highway
zaglavljen na sporom dijelu autoputa
is it gonna show up way busier on the
da li će se pokazati puno zaposlenijim na
highway than it actually is it's yeah I
autoput nego što zapravo jeste, da jesam
I personally use Waze which is owned by
Lično koristim Waze koji je u njegovom vlasništvu
Google it it's yeah it's I think it's
Google je, da, mislim da jeste
the exact same well no there's some
potpuno isti bunar ne postoji
enhanced features that Google Maps
poboljšane funkcije koje Google Maps
doesn't he'll differently yeah but what
zar on neće drugačije da, ali šta
I like about Waze is is that it is user
Sviđa mi se što je Waze to što je korisnik
input unlike a lot of Google Maps that
ulaz za razliku od većine Google Maps koji
is drawn by anonymous unit user data and
crtaju se anonimnim podacima korisnika jedinice i
things happening in the backend so ways
stvari se dešavaju u pozadini na taj način
builds off Google Maps but then you can
gradi Google mape, ali onda možete
add your individual components into it
dodajte svoje pojedinačne komponente u to
but I have at times I had a phone call
ali ponekad sam imao telefonski poziv
or text or something come in where it's
ili tekst ili nešto dolazi tamo gde je
like I need to respond to this so I'll
kao da moram da odgovorim na ovo pa ću i ja
pull over on the side of the road do the
povucite se sa strane ceste uradite
thing that I need to do and all sudden I
stvar koju trebam učiniti i odjednom se
get an alert on my phone we're detecting
primi upozorenje na moj telefon koji otkrivamo
a slowdown oh you know are you in
usporavanje oh znate da ste u
traffic how heavy is the traffic and I'm
saobraćaj koliko je promet gust i ja sam
like pulled over and so I'll say no and
poput povučenog pa ću reći ne i
move on this is this is odd
ovo je neobično
Jeff is not texting while driving no if
Jeff ne šalje tekst dok se vozi ne
this is out of character for you but
ovo je za vas neobično, ali
what what I could have done is gone
ono što sam mogao učiniti je nestalo
yes heavy traffic sure traffic's flowing
da gust promet siguran da promet teče
beside me but so I mean if there is that
pored mene, ali zato mislim ako to postoji
user element so I've never fully trusted
korisnički element, tako da se nikada nisam u potpunosti vjerovao
the information
informacije
see on those services because I know
vidjeti na tim uslugama jer znam
that there is that user input data right
da postoji taj unos podataka korisnika pravo
actually today on my way to the studio I
zapravo danas na putu za studio I
always use Google Maps I even though I
uvijek koristim Google Maps iako jesam
know how to get here I always use it I
znam kako doći ovdje Uvijek ga koristim
like I like to be told what to do but
kao da volim da mi se kaže šta da radim ali
Google told me to take the highway and I
Google mi je rekao da idem autoputem i ja
looked at the highway and I thought ah
pogledao prema autoputu i pomislio sam ah
that's a dead stop and Google was pretty
to je mrtva točka i Google je bio lijep
mad at me like they kept trying to
besan na mene kao da su to stalno pokušavali
direct me back to the highway but I was
usmerite me na autoput, ali jesam
like I am taking the main road was it
kao da idem glavnim putem bio je to
just that one spot and then I was fine
samo taj jedan spot i tada mi je bilo dobro
after I don't know yeah there's one spot
nakon što ne znam da, postoji jedno mesto
on the highway right now okay so this
na autoputu je odmah ok, pa ovo
this opens up something though
ovo ipak otvara nešto
interesting about and I know we need to
zanimljivo o i znam da to trebamo
move to the next story but about
prelazak na sljedeću priču ali o
proximity how specific is location-based
blizina koliko je specifična na lokaciji
services on the phone cuz like my kids
usluge na telefonu kao moja djeca
play pokemon go yeah so when they're at
igrajte pokemon, idi, pa kad su na
home if they move from one side of the
kući ako se presele sa jedne strane
living room to the next their character
dnevni boravak do sljedećeg njihova karaktera
moves with them yeah but when I'm
kreće s njima da, ali kad sam ja
sitting in the car I'm getting a bigger
sjedi u autu postajem veći
blip on the map and so I don't know if
pomičite kartu i tako da ne znam da li
it can update it as quick to my precise
može ga ažurirati kao brzo do mojih preciznosti
location it's probably lulling you into
lokacija u koju vas vjerojatno zaleđuje
a false sense of like anonymity it knows
lažno osećanje poput anonimnosti koje on poznaje
exactly where you it know exactly where
tačno tamo gde tačno znate gde
your park so then Google have not built
vaš park, tako da Google nije izgradio
something into the programming that it
nešto u programiranju da to
watches for the collection of devices
satovi za kolekciju uređaja
and it goes there are 99 within this box
a ide se da je 99 unutar ove kutije
that's not actual I think they will
to nije stvarno. Mislim da hoće
[Music]
[Muzika]